Okay, so let's talk about training,
pairing, and mentoring.
I really discuss a difference between the
three of these terms.
Now, training refers to an individual team
member gaining skill sets.
Right, so it's an individual team member
gaining their skill sets.
That is what training is.
As opposed to team development.
Don't confuse that with team development.
Now, training is an important part of team
development.
Absolutely is.
But team development itself refers to the
team coming together as a whole,
team interaction, team building.
That's what team development refers to,
right?
And training is one aspect
of that is an individual
team member gaining their own skill sets.
Now, team members want to gain their skill
sets, right?
So training can be to obviously fill in
gaps.
That's what training is, right?
or individuals, they
need to increase skill
sets because there's a
training gap somewhere.
They don't have the
appropriate technical skills
or management skills
or whatever it is, right?
But also at the beginning of a project,
the project manager themselves or the
team, right, or the team facilitator
themselves can always determine if there
are any specific training needs for that
particular project.
So in other words, all team
members need to go on a particular
training before they can
start working on this project.
So it might be a project-specific
training, it might be company-specific
training, it might be client-specific
training.
So, for example, training team members on
the methodology for this project.
What are the procedure, the basic
procedures for this new project?
Or client-specific methodology.
Before team members can roll onto an
external client project, before they can
roll onto the client site, for example,
they need to go on some specific training
to learn about the client, learn about the
procedures for the client
that they're working for.
So there might be some specific training
that all team members go on, but then
obviously there's going to be training
involved where team members are lacking in
some skill sets, they need to gain skill
sets.
Now, at the beginning of a project then,
or beginning of a release, then team
members, project manager, team
facilitator, agile coach, they need to
understand what training needs or they
need to anticipate these training needs.
So there's going to be a training plan.
They may create a training plan.
And training plan can obviously be created
throughout the project.
So training plan is a document.
It's an artifact.
And then they're going to be creating a
training calendar as well.
And then the calendar is going to be
showing the dates of the training,
location of the training and so and so
forth.
So the first thing, though, is to identify
the need for the training.
What is the actual need for the training?
So you need to identify
the competencies and
skill sets that's required to do the work.
And then you need to identify any
weaknesses.
You need to recognize any weaknesses
there.
Now, this is not just the project manager
or the team facilitator identifying that.
Individual team members will also identify
their strengths and weaknesses, right?
Team members, they may themselves identify
areas that they need to improve, right?
They themselves will want to go on
additional training, right?
Now, this also will be as a result of an
open air of communication, right?
So team members should not be considered,
you know, something negative.
So it should not be considered negative
that, oh, I don't have this skill set.
I better keep quiet about it, right?
No, you don't have a skill set.
Then you should be empowered to speak up
and say, I don't have this skill set.
I need some additional training.
Otherwise, how are team members going to
build trust?
How are they going to work together?
How are they going to build trust amongst
one another?
Now, training does not necessarily mean,
right?
It doesn't just necessarily mean that team
members are taking days off work.
and sitting in a class, right?
I mean, that is obviously, you
know, classroom is obviously
a type of training, but there's
also, you know, you have
synchronous training
and asynchronous training.
The training can also be
coaching on the job training,
job shadowing, that's all
part of synchronous training.
But then you could also have
asynchronous training, video
on demand, or even just
documentation reviews, for example.
Documentation review,
meaning your learning
assistant assistant, by reading a manual.
You could just be reading the manual,
following the instructions in the manual,
and then learning this particular system
or learning this particular process.
That can also include training.
And obviously, you know, training is going
to be different based on the industry and
the, you know, the type of project and the
type of skill set and so on and so forth.
Now, one of the biggest things,
though, regarding training, and a lot of
organizations do end up failing in this
area is that training Training should be
given as close to the point of solution as
it needed, right?
Close to the point where
the skill set is actually going
to be used, is actually
going to be utilized, right?
Not months and months in advance.
This happens all the time happens quite
often.
Team member will go on
training, but then they don't use
that skill set for another six
months or another 10 months.
Well, they've forgotten what they've
learned by then.
So it should always be as close.
those to the point of when it's actually
needed.
So that can actually utilize those skill
sets that they've learnt.
Now, of course, again, in reality,
there's many, many factors that determine
the timeline of the training,
when team members
are going on training and so and so forth.
Especially, you know, based on whether the
instructor is internal to the organization
or external to the organization,
right?
And then, you know,
what other commitments,
team members have and so on and so forth.
right and you know you can you can only
schedule like if it's a classroom training
you can only schedule it at certain points
right you can't just have on-demand
classroom training right so in that case
then they could have on-demand video
training right or documentation review and
that kind of stuff but again the idea is
it should be as close to the point as
needed okay now part of training then is
also going to include cost right training
is not free right training is going to
cost and so training should be part of
your project budget as well now if it's a
classroom training then you know books
materials instructional costs right even
venues for example right so you're
bringing in an external instructor that's
a very simple example let's say your team
decides to go on p&p training and you
bring in an external PMP instructor,
right?
So in-house, well, the availability of
that instructor is going to determine,
you know, when you're going to have that
training.
And then plus sometimes you might go to an
external venue.
Just go to an external venue, right,
a hotel conference room, for example.
Let's just get out of our office,
have everybody out of the office so,
you know, they can think in a,
you know, open mind, fresh mind,
they don't have to be worrying about work
all the time, right?
So let's take them to an external training
site.
So again, that all costs money and that's
all going to be part of your budget.
So that's a consideration to make at the
beginning of a project, right?
A consideration to make is what training
do team members need to go on,
as in company-specific training,
project-specific training, client-specific
training, that's all going to be part of
the budget.
But then what happens if we identify need
for additional training through,
say, halfway through the project?
What do we do in that situation?
So, you know, does that need to go through
a change control?
Does a budget need to be approved and so
on and so forth?
Right.
So additional training
and throughout might need
to go through an integrated
change control process.
Now, also something important to
understand when we're talking about
training, training does not just mean team
members.
Training can also be end users.
So we're developing a system.
We're implementing a brand new system or
we're creating a machine.
We're installing a machine.
Well, end users need training on that
machine.
End users need training on this system.
So again, all of these books,
instructional costs and so and so forth.
So that's a consideration
to make and that's
all going to be a direct
cost to your project.
And it's going to be part of your budget.
Right.
So again, always remember
that when we're talking
about training, it's not
just team members.
It might be talking about stakeholders as
well, other stakeholders like end users.
Now, what's the difference between pairing
and mentoring then?
Now, in both cases, pairing and mentoring,
the idea is to foster team collaboration,
right?
Team building, team collaboration,
building trust amongst one another, right?
Because team members are working together
in this case.
Or in this case, they're learning
together.
So pairing is where two team members are
learning from one another.
And typically what happens is,
let's say, you have two new team members,
join the team.
And they, you know, the junior team
members or the new team members,
they're learning about
the project, the learning
about the team, the learning
about the organization.
Well, they learn from one another.
Right.
So that's pairing.
Two team members learning from one
another.
Whereas mentoring is specific.
an experienced team member, coaching a
less experienced team member.
And in both cases, it's going to foster
building, right, team building,
collaboration, and building trust amongst
one another.
Now, there's also, there's
no point in sending team
members to training if they're
not going to learn anything.
So we need to measure the training
outcome.
What have they actually learned?
So during training, you may have a
pre-assessment and a post-assessment test.
So a pre-assessment, before they start the
training, what do these team members know?
And most of the time you expect the
pre-assessment scores to be really low.
But then immediately after the training,
you may create a baseline now.
What do you have a post-assessment test?
So what have team members gained?
What have the learned?
So the post-assessment, hopefully,
is they're going to score much higher.
what did it in the pre-assessment.
And either of those could be known as a
training baseline.
Either the pre-assessment
could be a training baseline
or the post-assessment
could be the training baseline.
And then from the
post-assessment then, team members
need to demonstrate how
well they actually understood.
They need to apply the knowledge that they
learned.
So that's how you'd measure
the training outcome by
demonstrating how well they're
actually performing now, right?
Demonstrating how well they're applying
the knowledge that they learned.
during the training.
So this section then, as I said,
we talked about training.
Training, a very important aspect of team
development.
So is mentoring, so is pairing and
coaching.
All important aspects of team development.